<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Blogula - A YK2 Dracula blog</title>
				
				<respStmt>
					<resp>created and encoded by</resp>
					<persName>Béatrice Pascale</persName>
					<note>Sample encoding done in the context of an assignment for the XSLT class of the M2 TNAH.</note>
				</respStmt>
				
			</titleStmt>
			
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Ecole nationale des Chartes</publisher>
				<pubPlace> 65, Rue de Richelieu, <placeName>Paris</placeName></pubPlace>
				<date when="2026-04"/>
				
			</publicationStmt>
			
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl>
					<title>Dracula</title>
					<author>Bram Stoker</author>
					<publisher>Grosset &amp; Dunlap</publisher>
					<pubPlace> The Country Life Press, Garden City, <placeName>New York</placeName></pubPlace>
					<date when="1897"/>
					<!-- J'ai utilisé la version de Dracula du Projet Gutenberg pour cet encodage, je joins le lien ci-dessous -->
					<idno type="url">https://gutenberg.org/files/345/345-h/345-h.htm</idno>
				</bibl>
				
				<listPerson>
					<person></person>
				</listPerson>
				
				<listPlace>
					<place></place>
				</listPlace>
				
			</sourceDesc>
			
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:id="ch1">

			<div type="header">
				<head type="chapter_title">Chapter 1</head>
				<div xml:id="chapter_subtitle">
					<p n="1"><persName ref="jonathan_001">Jonathan Harker</persName>'s Journal</p>
					<!--Mettre en italique lors de la transformation-->
					<p n="2">(Kept in shorthand.)</p>
				</div>
			</div>

			<div type="entry" xml:id="ch1-e1">
				<dateline> 3 May. <placeName>Bistritz</placeName></dateline>
				
				<p n="1">Left Munich at 8:35 P. M., on <date>1st May</date>, arriving at <placeName>Vienna</placeName> 
					early next morning; should have arrived at 6:46, but train was an hour late. 
					<placeName>Buda-Pesth</placeName> seems a wonderful place, from the glimpse which I got of it 
					from the train and the little I could walk through the streets. I feared to go very far from 
					the station, as we had arrived late and would start as near the correct time as possible. 
					The impression I had was that we were leaving the West and entering the East; the most western 
					of splendid bridges over the <geogName>Danube</geogName>, which is here of noble width and depth,
					took us among the traditions of Turkish rule.</p>
				
				
				<p n="2">We left in pretty good time, and came after nightfall to <placeName>Klausenburgh</placeName>. Here I stopped for 
					the night at the Hotel Royale. I had for dinner, or rather supper, a chicken done up some way 
					with red pepper, which was very good but thirsty. (Mem., get recipe for <persName ref="mina_001">Mina</persName>.) I asked the waiter,
					and he said it was called “paprika hendl,” and that, as it was a national dish, I should be able 
					to get it anywhere along <geogName>the Carpathians</geogName>. I found my smattering of <lang>German</lang> very useful here; indeed,
					I don’t know how I should be able to get on without it.</p>
				
				<p n="3">Having had some time at my disposal when in <placeName>London</placeName>, I had visited the <placeName>British Museum</placeName>,
					and made search among the books and maps in the library regarding <placeName>Transylvania</placeName>; 
					it had struck me that some foreknowledge of the country could hardly fail to have 
					some importance in dealing with a nobleman of that country. I find that the district he 
					named is in the extreme east of the country, just on the borders of three states, <placeName>Transylvania</placeName>, 
					<placeName>Moldavia</placeName> and <placeName>Bukovina</placeName>, in the midst of <geogName>the Carpathian mountains</geogName>; 
					one of the wildest and least known portions of <placeName>Europe</placeName>. I was not able to light on any map or 
					work giving the exact locality of the <placeName>Castle Dracula</placeName>, as there are no maps of this country as
					yet to compare with our own Ordnance Survey maps; but I found that <placeName>Bistritz</placeName>, the post town named
					by <persName ref="dracula_001">Count Dracula</persName>, is a fairly well-known place. I shall enter here some of my notes, as they may 
					refresh my memory when I talk over my travels with <persName ref="mina_001">Mina</persName>.</p>
				
				<p n="4">In the population of <placeName>Transylvania</placeName> there are four distinct nationalities: Saxons in the South, and mixed 
					with them the Wallachs, who are the descendants of the Dacians; Magyars in the West, and Szekelys in the East 
					and North. I am going among the latter, who claim to be descended from Attila and the Huns. This may be so, 
					for when the Magyars conquered the country in the eleventh century they found the Huns settled in it. 
					I read that every known superstition in the world is gathered into the horseshoe of the Carpathians, 
					as if it were the centre of some sort of imaginative whirlpool; if so my stay may be very interesting. 
					(Mem., I must ask the Count all about them.)</p>
				
				<closer>
					<salute>I am with all my Heart<lb/>Dear Friend<lb/>Yours most
						faithfully</salute>
					<signed>Werlhof</signed>
					<address>
						<addrLine>à Monsieur</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Monsieur Haller</addrLine>
						<addrLine>conseiller aulique et<lb/>professeur roïal</addrLine>
						<addrLine>à<lb/>Göttingen</addrLine>
					</address>
				</closer>
			</div>


		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
