<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Jonathan Harker’s Journal: 4 May</title>
				
				<respStmt>
					<resp>encoded by</resp>
					<persName>Beatrice Pascale</persName>
					<note>Encoding and transformation done in the context of an assignment for the XSLT class of the M2 TNAH.</note>
				</respStmt>
				
			</titleStmt>
			
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Ecole nationale des Chartes</publisher>
				<pubPlace> 65, Rue de Richelieu, <placeName>Paris</placeName></pubPlace>
				<date when="2026-04-02"/>
				
			</publicationStmt>
			
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl>
					<title>Dracula</title>
					<author>Bram Stoker</author>
					<publisher>Grosset &amp; Dunlap</publisher>
					<pubPlace> The Country Life Press, Garden City, <placeName>New York</placeName></pubPlace>
					<date when="1897"/>
					<!-- J'ai utilisé la version de Dracula du Projet Gutenberg pour cet encodage, je joins le lien ci-dessous -->
					<idno type="url">https://gutenberg.org/files/345/345-h/345-h.htm</idno>
				</bibl>
				
				
				<listPerson>
					<person xml:id="JHarker">
						<persName>Jonathan Harker</persName>
					</person>
					<person xml:id="CDracula">
						<persName>Count Dracula</persName>
					</person>
					<person xml:id="MMurray">
						<persName>Mina Murray</persName>
					</person>
				</listPerson>
				
				<listPlace>
					<place xml:id="Bistritz">
						<placeName>Bistritz (Bistrița)</placeName>
						<location>
							<country>Romania</country>
							<geo>47.1333 24.5000</geo>
						</location>
					</place>
				</listPlace>
				
			</sourceDesc>
			
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body xml:id="ch1">
			<div type="header">
				<head type="chapter_title">Chapter 1</head>
				<div xml:id="chapter_subtitle">
					<p n="1"><persName ref="#JHarker">Jonathan Harker</persName>'s Journal</p>
					<p n="2">(Kept in shorthand.)</p>
				</div>
			</div>
			
			<div type="entry" xml:id="ch1-e2">
				<dateline><date when="1893-05-04">4 May</date>.</dateline>
				
				<p n="10">—I found that my landlord had got a letter from the <persName ref="#CDracula">Count</persName>, directing him to secure the best place on the coach for me; but on making inquiries as to details he seemed somewhat reticent, &amp; pretended that he could not understand my <lang xml:lang="de">German</lang>. This could not be true, because up to then he had understood it perfectly; at least, he answered my questions exactly as if he did. He and his wife, the <persName ref="#OldLady">old lady</persName> who had received me, looked at each other in a frightened sort of way. He mumbled out that the money had been sent in a letter, and that was all he knew. When I asked him if he knew <persName ref="#CDracula">Count Dracula</persName>, and could tell me anything of his <placeName ref="#DracCastle">castle</placeName>, both he and his wife crossed themselves, and, saying that they knew nothing at all, simply refused to speak further. It was so near the time of starting that I had no time to ask any one else, for it was all very mysterious and not by any means comforting.</p>
				
				<p n="11">Just before I was leaving, the <persName ref="#OldLady">old lady</persName> came up to my room and said in a very hysterical way: <q>“Must you go? Oh! young <foreign xml:lang="de">Herr</foreign>, must you go?”</q> She was in such an excited state that she seemed to have lost her grip of what <lang xml:lang="de">German</lang> she knew, and mixed it all up with some other language which I did not know at all. I was just able to follow her by asking many questions. When I told her that I must go at once, and that I was engaged on important business, she asked again: <q>“Do you know what day it is?”</q> I answered that it was the <date when="1893-05-04">fourth of May</date>. She shook her head as she said again: <q>“Oh, yes! I know that! I know that, but do you know what day it is?”</q> On my saying that I did not understand, she went on: <q>“It is the eve of <date when="--05-04">St. George’s Day</date>. Do you not know that to-night, when the clock strikes midnight, all the evil things in the world will have full sway? Do you know where you are going, and what you are going to?”</q></p>
				
				<p n="12">She was in such evident distress that I tried to comfort her, but without effect. Finally she went down on her knees and implored me not to go; at least to wait a day or two before starting. It was all very ridiculous but I did not feel comfortable. However, there was business to be done, and I could allow nothing to interfere with it. I therefore tried to raise her up, and said, as gravely as I could, that I thanked her, but my duty was imperative, and that I must go. She then rose and dried her eyes, and taking a <rs type="object">crucifix</rs> from her neck offered it to me. I did not know what to do, for, as an <rs type="religious">English Churchman</rs>, I have been taught to regard such things as in some measure idoltrous, and yet it seemed so ungracious to refuse an old lady meaning so well and in such a state of mind. She saw, I suppose, the doubt in my face, for she put the <rs type="object">rosary</rs> round my neck, and said, <q>“For your mother’s sake,”</q> and went out of the room.</p>
				
				<p n="13">I am writing up this part of the diary whilst I am waiting for the coach, which is, of course, late; and the <rs type="object">crucifix</rs> is still round my neck. Whether it is the old lady’s fear, or the many ghostly traditions of this place, or the <rs type="object">crucifix</rs> itself, I do not know, but I am not feeling nearly as easy in my mind as usual. If this book should ever reach <persName ref="#MMurray">Mina</persName> before I do, let it bring my good-bye. Here comes the coach!</p>
			
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
